<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Scientific logbook (Posts about blog)</title><link>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/categories/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:laurent.perrinet@univ-amu.fr"&gt;Laurent Perrinet&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.5/ar/"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons License BY-NC-SA"
style="border-width:0; margin-bottom:12px;"
src="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/2.5/ar/88x31.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 05:20:31 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Modelling wind ripples</title><link>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2023-04-16-modelling-wind-ripples.html</link><dc:creator>Laurent Perrinet</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, I try to simulate the patterns obtained on a sandy terrain. This is what is observed when the wind blows on the dry surface of a land with sand or also on the surface of the sea in the presence of currents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As described in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dune"&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dune&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a sandy seabed is subject to wave action and the wave orbital motion is strong enough to move sand grains, ripples often appear. The ripples induced by wave action are called “wave ripples”; their characteristics being different from those of the ripples generated by steady flows. The most striking difference between wave ripple fields and current ripple fields is the regularity of the former. Indeed, regular long-crested wave ripple fields are often observed on tidal beaches from which the sea has withdrawn at low water (see figure 1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A nice example is shown in &lt;a href="http://www.coastalwiki.org/wiki/Wave_ripple_formation"&gt;http://www.coastalwiki.org/wiki/Wave_ripple_formation&lt;/a&gt; showing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ripples observed at Sea Rim State Park, along the coast of east Texas close to the border with Louisiana (courtesy by Zoltan Sylvester).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.coastalwiki.org/w/images/6/65/WaveRippleFormationFig0.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.coastalwiki.org/wiki/Wave_ripple_formation"&gt;Wave ripple formation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting aspect of that patterns is that they may occur at different scales, like taht example on the surface of the Mars planet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overview of large sand wave field and high-resolution difference map of two surveys approximately 21 hours apart illustrating both large-scale and small-scale sand wave migration and orientation. Migration is from right to left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Daniel-Hanes/publication/252161559/figure/fig1/AS:669991225552924@1536749764962/Overview-of-large-sand-wave-field-and-high-resolution-difference-map-of-two-surveys.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2023-04-16-modelling-wind-ripples.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (19 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>art</category><category>blog</category><category>nature</category><category>numpy</category><category>open-science</category><category>python</category><category>trames</category><guid>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2023-04-16-modelling-wind-ripples.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 17:30:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Implementing a retinotopic transform using `grid_sample` from pyTorch</title><link>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2023-02-02-implementing-a-retinotopic-transform-using-grid_sample-from-pytorch.html</link><dc:creator>Laurent Perrinet</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="Implementing-a-retinotopic-transform-using-grid_sample-from-pyTorch"&gt;Implementing a retinotopic transform using &lt;code&gt;grid_sample&lt;/code&gt; from &lt;code&gt;pyTorch&lt;/code&gt;&lt;a class="anchor-link" href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2023-02-02-implementing-a-retinotopic-transform-using-grid_sample-from-pytorch.html#Implementing-a-retinotopic-transform-using-grid_sample-from-pyTorch"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://pytorch.org/docs/stable/generated/torch.nn.functional.grid_sample.html"&gt;grid_sample&lt;/a&gt; transform is a powerful function which allows to transform any input image into a new topology. It is notably used in &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1506.02025"&gt;Spatial Transformer Networks&lt;/a&gt; for instance to learn CNN to be invariant to affine transforms. We used it recently in a publication &lt;a href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/publication/dabane-22/"&gt;What You See Is What You Transform: Foveated Spatial Transformers as a Bio-Inspired Attention Mechanism&lt;/a&gt; by Ghassan Dabane &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of &lt;code&gt;grid_sample&lt;/code&gt; can b etedious and here, we show how to use it to create a log-polar transform of the image and create the following figure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/laurentperrinet/2023-01-31_formes-et-perception/main/content/images/retinotopy.png" alt="Retinotopy"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A picture (extract from the painting &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Ambassadors_(Holbein))"&gt;"The Ambassadors" by Hans Holbein the Younger&lt;/a&gt; can be represented on a regular grid represented by vertical (red) and horizontal (blue) lines. Retinotopy transforms this grid, and in particular the area representing the fovea (shaded gray) is over-represented. Applied to the original image of the portrait, the image is strongly distorted and represents more finally the parts under the axis of sight (here the mouth).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2023-02-02-implementing-a-retinotopic-transform-using-grid_sample-from-pytorch.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (5 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>blog</category><category>deep-learning</category><category>machine-learning</category><category>open-science</category><category>python</category><category>pytorch</category><category>retina</category><category>vision</category><guid>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2023-02-02-implementing-a-retinotopic-transform-using-grid_sample-from-pytorch.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 07:59:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections présidentielles 2022: estimation du transfert de voix</title><link>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2022-06-08-transfert-de-voix.html</link><dc:creator>Laurent Perrinet</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tl;dr : &lt;em&gt;On essaie ici de deviner le transfert des voix entre les choix effectués entre deux scrutins d'un vote (ici les élections présidentielles 2022 en France) par une méthode d'&lt;a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apprentissage_automatique"&gt;apprentissage automatique&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/badge/latestdoi/488514016"&gt;&lt;img src="https://zenodo.org/badge/488514016.svg" alt="DOI"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afin d'analyser les résultats des élections, par exemple les dernières élections présidentielles de 2022 en France, et de mieux comprendre la dynamique des choix de vote entre les différents groupes de population, il peut être utile d'utiliser des outils d'&lt;a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apprentissage_automatique"&gt;apprentissage automatique&lt;/a&gt; pour inférer des structures à première vue cachées dans la masse des données. En particulier, inspiré par cet &lt;a href="https://www.lemonde.fr/les-decodeurs/article/2022/05/04/election-presidentielle-2022-quels-reports-de-voix-entre-les-deux-tours_6124672_4355770.html"&gt;article du Monde&lt;/a&gt;, on peut se poser la question de savoir &lt;em&gt;si on peut extraire depuis les données brutes des élections une estimation du report de voix entre les choix de vote au premier tour et ceux qui sont effectués au deuxième tour&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pour cela, parmi les outils mathématiques de l'apprentissage automatique, nous allons utiliser des probabilités. Cette théorie va nous permettre d'exprimer le fait que les résultats tels qu'ils sont obtenus peuvent présenter une variabilité mais que celle-ci réelle résulte de préférences de chaque individu dans la population votante. En particulier, on peut considérer que chaque individu va avoir une préférence, graduée entre $0=0\%$ et $1=100\%$ pour chacun des choix (candidats, nul, blanc, abstention) au premier et second tour. Ainsi, les votes effectués vont correspondre à la réalisation de ces préférences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bien sûr, le vote reste secret et on n'a pas accès au vote de chaque individu et encore moins à ses préférences. Mais comme chaque bureau de vote présente des variabilités liées au contexte local et qui fait que cette population locale a une préférence pour certains choix plutôt que d'autres, on peut considérer chaque bureau de vote comme une population individuelle pour lequel nous allons essayer de prédire les résultats du vote au deuxième tour. &lt;strong&gt;En exploitant les irrégularités locales, bureau de vote par bureau de vote, nous allons pouvoir prédire (le mieux possible) le report des votes individuel (de chaque individu tel qu'il passe d'un vote à un autre, par exemple de "Hidalgo" à "Macron").&lt;/strong&gt; Nous allons en particulier montrer une prédiction très correcte des données du second tour à partir de ceux du premier, montrant la plausibilité d'une telle hypothèse :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/laurentperrinet/2022-05-04_transfert-des-voix/main/2022-06-08_prediction_transfert-des-voix_bce.png" alt="Prédiction du transfert des voix" title="Prédiction du transfert des voix"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C'est à ma connaissance une contribution originale (jusqu'à ce qu'une bonne âme veuille bien me donner un lien vers une méthode existante similaire qui me permette de correctement la citer...) que nous allons exploiter ici. Cette prédiction, si elle est efficace (et on va montrer qu'elle est en moyenne correctement prédite avec moins de 2 points de pourcentages d'erreur près), peut donner une idée du transfert de vote entre les deux tours qui a lieu en fonction des préférences des votes de chaque individu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nous allons dans la suite montrer comment on peut estimer le pourcentage de chances d'exprimer une voix pour un candidat ou pour l'autre en fonction du choix qu'on a exprimé au premier tour:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/laurentperrinet/2022-05-04_transfert-des-voix/main/2022-06-06_transfert-des-voix.png" alt="Transfert des voix" title="Transfert des voix"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comme on le verra plus bas, ce tableau montre des tendances claires, par exemple que si on a voté "Macron", "Jadot", "Hidalgo" ou "Pécresse" au premier tour, alors on va certainement voter "Macron" au deuxième tour. Ces électeurs se montrent particulièrement consensuel et suivent le « pacte républicain » mise en place pour faire un "barrage" au Front National (en suivant le terme consacré). Il montre aussi que si on a voté "Le Pen" ou "Dupont-Aignan" au premier tour alors on va voter Le Pen au deuxième, un clair vote de suivi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connaissant les couleurs politiques d'autres candidats du premier tour, on peut être surpris que les électeurs de "Arthaud", "Roussel", "Lassalle" ou "Poutou" ont majoritairement choisi "Le Pen" au deuxième tour, signifiant alors un rejet du candidat Macron. Les électeurs de Zemmour sont aussi partagés, signifiant un rejet des deux alternatives. &lt;strong&gt;Ce résultat est à prendre avec des pincettes car ces derniers candidats ont obtenu moins de votes et donc que le processus d'inférence est forcément moins précis car il y a moins de données disponibles.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En résumé, cette analyse donne des tendances en fonction des choix exprimés au premier tour:
&lt;img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/laurentperrinet/2022-05-04_transfert-des-voix/main/2022-06-08_transfert-des-voix_tendances.png" alt="Transfert des voix" title="Tendances présidentielle 2022"&gt;
qui montre une nette séparation des groupes de vote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2022-06-08-transfert-de-voix.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (47 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>blog</category><category>deep-learning</category><category>grand-public</category><category>machine-learning</category><category>open-science</category><category>pandas</category><category>python</category><category>pytorch</category><guid>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2022-06-08-transfert-de-voix.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 19:27:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>COSYNE reviewer feedback</title><link>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2022-02-11-cosyne-reviewer-feedback.html</link><dc:creator>Laurent Perrinet</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tl;dr : &lt;em&gt;Crowd-sourcing raw scores for your COSYNE reviewer feedback.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following that message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear community,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;COSYNE is a great conference which plays a pivotal role in our field. If you have submitted an abstract (or several) you have recently received your scores. I am not affiliated to COSYNE - yet willing to contribute in some way: I would like to ask one minute of your time to report the raw scores from your reviewers. I will summarize in a few lines the results in one week time (11/02). The more numerous your feedbacks the better their precision!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of 2022-02-20, I had received $N = 98$ answers from the &lt;a href="https://forms.gle/hjzWVemM4Jy9cBbZ9"&gt;google form&lt;/a&gt; (out of them, $95$ are valid) out of the $881$ submitted abstracts. In short, the result is that the total score $S$ is simply the linear sum of the scores $s_i$ given by each reviewer $i$ relatively weighted by the confidence levels $\pi_i$ (as stated in the email we received from the chairs):&lt;/p&gt;
$$
S = \frac{ \sum_i \pi_i\cdot s_i}{\sum_i \pi_i}
$$&lt;p&gt;Or if you prefer
$$
S = \sum_i  \frac{\pi_i}{\sum_j \pi_j} \cdot s_i
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We deduce from that formula that the threshold is close to $6.34$ this year:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://github.com/laurentperrinet/2022-02-11_COSYNE-scoresheet/raw/main/2022-02-11_COSYNE-razor.png" alt="2022-02-11_COSYNE-razor"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More details in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/laurentperrinet/2022-02-11_COSYNE-scoresheet/blob/main/2022-02-11_COSYNE-scoresheet.ipynb"&gt;notebook&lt;/a&gt; (or directly in this &lt;a href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2022-02-11-cosyne-reviewer-feedback.html"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;) which can also be &lt;a href="https://github.com/laurentperrinet/2022-02-11_COSYNE-scoresheet"&gt;forked here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://mybinder.org/v2/gh/laurentperrinet/2022-02-11_COSYNE-scoresheet/main?labpath=2022-02-11_COSYNE-scoresheet.ipynb"&gt;interactively modified on binder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EDIT: On 2022-02-20, I have updated the notebook to account for new answers, I have now received $N = 98$ answers (out of them, $95$ are valid), yet nothing changed qualitatively. On 2022-02-11, I had received $N = 82$ answers from the &lt;a href="https://forms.gle/hjzWVemM4Jy9cBbZ9"&gt;google form&lt;/a&gt; (out of them, $79$ are valid) and the estimated threshold wass close to $6.05$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2022-02-11-cosyne-reviewer-feedback.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (12 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>blog</category><category>open-science</category><category>pandas</category><category>python</category><guid>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2022-02-11-cosyne-reviewer-feedback.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2022 11:35:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Dreamachine</title><link>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2022-01-30-dreamachine.html</link><dc:creator>Laurent Perrinet</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's at the &lt;a href="https://miam.org/"&gt;MIAM&lt;/a&gt; (Miam Musée International des Arts Modestes) in Sète, France, that I could for the first time experience really the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dreamachine"&gt;Dreamachine&lt;/a&gt;. It's an optical system which consists of a central light which is periodically occluded by a rotating (cardboard?) cylinder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The magic of it is that the frequency of occlusion is around $12$ Hz, an important resonant state for sensory system. For the first time, I could really try it out at the MIAM - the important point being to close your lids and rest quiet while looking at the stroboscopic light source. Surprisingly, you see the emergence of "psychedelic patterns" (of course, less than in hippie's movies) yet of the order of the color pattern that may arise in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fechner_color"&gt;Benham's Disk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's difficult to reproduce this pattern on a screen, yet it is still possible to give an &lt;em&gt;impression of it&lt;/em&gt;. The goal is here :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;to generate a complex visual stimulation flickering on average at $12$ Hz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;to project it on a retinotopic space to maximise the "psychelic" effect&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/files/2022-01-30-dreamachine/retino_alpha.gif" alt="retino_alpha"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2022-01-30-dreamachine.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (16 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>art</category><category>blog</category><category>grand-public</category><category>motionclouds</category><category>outreach</category><category>python</category><category>space</category><category>v1</category><guid>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2022-01-30-dreamachine.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 30 Jan 2022 10:33:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Find a 8 in a forest of 9</title><link>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2021-12-01-find-a-8-in-a-forest-of-9.html</link><dc:creator>Laurent Perrinet</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal here is to find one non-repeting pattern in an image. First, find the pattern, then second, compute correlation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2021-12-01-find-a-8-in-a-forest-of-9.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>art</category><category>blog</category><category>grand-public</category><category>math</category><category>outreach</category><category>python</category><category>space</category><guid>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2021-12-01-find-a-8-in-a-forest-of-9.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 20:30:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Triangulating stars on the night sky</title><link>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2021-12-01-triangulating-stars-on-the-night-sky.html</link><dc:creator>Laurent Perrinet</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a previous notebook, I have shown properties of the &lt;a href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2021-03-27-density-of-stars-on-the-surface-of-the-sky.html"&gt;distribution of stars in the sky&lt;/a&gt;. Here, I would like to use the existing database of stars' positions and display them as a triangulation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2021-12-01-triangulating-stars-on-the-night-sky.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (7 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>art</category><category>blog</category><category>grand-public</category><category>outreach</category><category>python</category><category>space</category><guid>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2021-12-01-triangulating-stars-on-the-night-sky.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 09:32:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Modelling Ocean surface waves</title><link>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2021-09-11-modelling-ocean-surface-waves.html</link><dc:creator>Laurent Perrinet</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to model Ocean surface waves, I have played using a &lt;a href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2014-10-24_a-bit-of-fun-with-gravity-waves.html"&gt;linear superposition of sinusoids&lt;/a&gt; and also on the fact that &lt;a href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2016-04-24_a-wave-going-backwards.html"&gt;phase speed (following a wave's crest) is twice as fast as group speed (following a group of waves)&lt;/a&gt;. Finally, I more recently used such generation of a model of the random superposition of waves to model the &lt;a href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2020-06-19-caustic-optics.html"&gt;wigggling lines formed by the refraction (bendings of the trajectory of a ray at the interface between air and water) of light, called caustics&lt;/a&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observing real-life ocean waves instructed me that if a single wave is well approximated by a sinusoïd, each wave is qualitatively a bit different. Typical for these surface gravity waves are &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stokes_wave"&gt;the sharp crests and flat troughs&lt;/a&gt;. As a matter of fact, modelling ocean waves is on one side very useful (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ocean_dynamics"&gt;Ocean dynamics&lt;/a&gt; and its impact on climate, modelling tides, tsunamis, diffraction in a bay to predict coastline evolution, ...) but quite demanding despite a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Airy_wave_theory"&gt;well known mathematical model&lt;/a&gt;. Starting with the Navier-Stokes equations to an incompressible fluid (water) in a gravitational field leads to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luke%27s_variational_principle"&gt;Luke's variational principle&lt;/a&gt; in certain simplifying conditions. Further simplifications lead to the approximate solution given by Stokes which gives the following shape as the sum of different harmonics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/cb/Stokes3_wave.svg/2880px-Stokes3_wave.svg.png" alt="Stokes wave(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stokes_wave)"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems well enough at the moment and I will capture this shape in this notebook and notably if that applies to a random mixture of such waves...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(WORK IN PROGRESS)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current situation is that these solutions seem to not fit what is displayed on the wikipedia page and that I do not spot the bug I may have introduced... More work on this is needed and any feedback is welcome...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2021-09-11-modelling-ocean-surface-waves.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (5 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>art</category><category>blog</category><category>elasticite</category><category>math</category><category>python</category><guid>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2021-09-11-modelling-ocean-surface-waves.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 11 Sep 2021 09:56:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Density of stars on the surface of the sky</title><link>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2021-03-27-density-of-stars-on-the-surface-of-the-sky.html</link><dc:creator>Laurent Perrinet</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/badge/latestdoi/191391751"&gt;&lt;img src="https://zenodo.org/badge/191391751.svg" alt="DOI"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the night sky, the pattern of stars on the surface of the sky follows a familiar pattern. The Big Dipper, Cassiopeia, the Pleiades, or Orion are popular landmarks in the sky which we can immediatly recognize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different civilisations labelled these patterns using names such as constellations in the western world. However, this pattern is often the result of pure chance. Stars from one constellation belong often to remote areas in the universe and they bear this familiarity only because we always saw them as such; the rate at which stars move is much shorter than the lifespan of humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am curious here to study the density of stars as they appear on the surface of the sky. It is both a simple question yet a complex to formulate. Is there any generic principle that could be used to characterize their distribution? This is my attempt to answer the question&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://astronomy.stackexchange.com/questions/43147/density-of-stars-on-the-surface-of-the-sky"&gt;https://astronomy.stackexchange.com/questions/43147/density-of-stars-on-the-surface-of-the-sky&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(but also to make the formulation of the question clearer...). This is my answer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2021-03-27-density-of-stars-on-the-surface-of-the-sky.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (33 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>blog</category><category>grand-public</category><category>math</category><category>moviepy</category><category>outreach</category><category>python</category><category>space</category><guid>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2021-03-27-density-of-stars-on-the-surface-of-the-sky.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Mar 2021 13:06:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Time lapsing an orchid's flower</title><link>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2021-02-21-time-lapsing-an-orchids-flower.html</link><dc:creator>Laurent Perrinet</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal here is to realize a time-lapse using a raspberry π and some python code and finally get this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://github.com/laurentperrinet/TimeTeleScope/raw/main/videos/2021-02-17_TimeTeleScope.gif" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This was done over 10 days, with &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; each day an &lt;em&gt;irregular&lt;/em&gt; session the morning and one in the evening)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2021-02-21-time-lapsing-an-orchids-flower.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (7 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>blog</category><category>grand-public</category><category>learning</category><category>moviepy</category><category>numpy</category><category>outreach</category><category>python</category><category>vision</category><guid>https://laurentperrinet.github.io/sciblog/posts/2021-02-21-time-lapsing-an-orchids-flower.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 19:57:52 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>